Do my eyes deceive me or do you have the
anxiety sweats about learning everything
you need to know about a push unit one?
Well, this video is about to dry up all
that flop sweat. So, if you're ready to
get them brain cows milked, let's get to
it. First of all, let me give you the
big picture of this unit so you know
where everything is headed. The time
period is 1491 to6007, which is to say a
year before Columbus arrived in the New
World until the establishment of
Jamestown, the first British colony in
North America. Now, we're going to start
by exploring the social and political
landscape of the indigenous peoples in
the Americas. And then we'll talk about
why those rascally Europeans even showed
up to begin with. And then we'll
consider the effects of the European
intrusion in the Americas. And let me
just tell you, it gets saucy. So, huh,
buckle up. Okay. Now, before we go
meeting all these indigenous groups and
explore how they lived, let me just tell
you what you cannot afford to forget
about this topic. The native populations
in the Americas were diverse and varied.
And of equal importance, geography
played a significant role in the
development of those differences. I
cannot overestimate how important that
point is. Write it down. Tattoo it on
your forehead if you must, but do not
forget it. The reason I'm flapping my
mouth hole so vehemently about it is
that there's this persistent
misunderstanding about exactly who
populated the Americas before European
content. And here to tell us about it is
our new friend, dimwitted Derek. Now, I
thought all Native Americans was the
same. What was all their teepeees and
whatnot? Oh, Derek, my dim-witted cod.
No other way to say this, but uh you
basic. It's a devastating insult. You're
devastated right now. No. Indigenous
societies were every bit as varied and
diverse as societies on any other
continent. Italians and Germans not the
same. Chinese and Japanese emphatically
not the same. And so it is with many
indigenous societies in the Americas.
Okay, so with that established, let's go
ahead and meet some of these groups. But
first, a word from the sponsor of the
creation of many of these diverse
societies, namely Maze. Now, this tasty
crop that we know as corn was first
cultivated in what is today southern
Mexico by at least 5,000 B.CE CE and
then spread throughout the Americas via
trade networks and migration routes. And
this is important because as maze became
the staple crop of various peoples
throughout the Americas that led to the
creation of larger and more complex
society. For example, there in central
Mexico you have the Aztec Empire with
its giant honking capital city of Tennos
Titlon. And without maze cultivation,
that massive urban dwelling probably
would have been impossible to create.
And why says you? Well, says I. Because
for societies that adopted maze
cultivation, four effects usually
follow. But first, let me mention that
this video is part of a larger resource
that's going to help you get an A in
your class and a five on your exam in
May. It's my A pushheimly review guide,
and it's got everything you need to
study as fast as possible, including
exclusive videos that are not here on
YouTube, practice questions, practice
exams, and all the rest. So, if that's
something that you're into, that link is
in the description below. Okay, back to
the effects of maze cultivation. The
first effect is economic development.
You see, since larger societies
typically trade with other societies,
that typically leads to more boom boom
for all involved because surplus food
frees up more of the population to
specialize in other kinds of work that
can be traded with others. Second, maze
cultivation leads to permanent
settlements. In case you never grown a
crop in your life, you might not know
that in order to do it, you kind of have
to stick around and tend to those crops.
So, for many societies that adopted maze
cultivation, they became what we call
sedentary, which is to say located in
one place instead of moving around. So
when people get all sedentary like more
complex political and social structures
can develop that aren't possible in a
nomadic society. Third, it led to the
development of advanced irrigation
techniques. Now irrigation is just the
process of diverting natural water
sources like rivers or streams towards
crops. And fourth, maze cultivation led
to social diversification, which was
also the case in early civilizations all
across the world. Now, social
diversification is just a fancy way of
saying that when a settlement or society
becomes more complex, labor becomes more
specialized and social hierarchies
developed to organize the people into
more powerful and less powerful groups.
All right, now I know we're all having a
blast talking about maze cultivation,
but I reckon it's high time that we meet
some of these native societies and see
how geography shaped their way of life.
So, just for poops and giggles, let's
start over here and meet the societies
of the Northeast, Mississippi River
Valley, and the Atlantic coast. But hey,
make sure you know at least one specific
example from each of these regions, even
if they're not the ones that I
mentioned. Okay, here in the Northeast,
let me introduce you to the Irakcoy.
Now, they were semi-sedentary and relied
on maze and other staple crops for
survival. Because there are metric
buttloads of trees in this region that
determined the kind of infrastructure
they built for their society, namely the
long house. Now, this is a structure in
which multiple generations of a family
would live together, sometimes up to 200
of them. Then, further south, meet the
Cherokee. Now, maze cultivation reached
them about a th000 B.CE. along with
beans and squash which meant that their
society was built around agriculture.
However, they would also qualify as
semi-edentary because men still hunted
for meat while women usually tended the
crops and they moved around according to
the seasons to gather wild crops. In
fact, like many other indigenous groups,
Cherokee women had far more social
capital than their European
counterparts. And that means that many
of their cultures were matrinal, meaning
that power and possessions were passed
down through generations on the mother's
side, not the fathers.
>> Well, that don't sound right.
>> Well, yeah, Derek. Not in Europe where
everything was real patriarchal and
focused on the men folk, but that's how
it was here in the Americas. And then
moving west, let me introduce you to a
group of societies known as the
Mississippian cultures. Now, because of
the abundance of rich soil around the
Mississippi and Ohio river valleys,
these people were able to exist in large
towns, about 4,000 to 6,000 in
population. Also, since they live near
complex river systems, they traded
extensively with other groups. And all
of this meant, like I said before, that
these societies became more complex with
the development of social hierarchies.
And the largest of the Mississippian
settlements was Cahokia in which
something like 10 to 20,000 people
lived.
>> Now that is a lot of teepeees.
>> Derek, they did not live in teepee. It
was like an urban environment, like a
city. Whatever. Let's just keep moving
west into the Great Basin and Great
Plains regions. Now, because the climate
of these regions is real hot and dry,
indigenous groups living here responded
to their environment by developing
nomadic lifestyles, which is to say they
moved around instead of staying in one
place. And a good example here is our
friends, the Ute. Now, they lived in
groups of 20 to 100 extended family
groups and moved through the region on a
seasonal basis while living in mobile
shelters like animal skin tepeees.
>> I knew it.
>> Yeah, some indigenous groups did live in
teepeees and the ute were one of them.
Ute men were typically responsible for
hunting animals like deer, analopee, and
most of all buffalo while women gathered
berries and roots. And finally, let's
move all the way to the northwest and
present day California. And in general,
these societies did not practice
agriculture. And that might make you
think that they were nomadic like the
Great Basin and the Great Plains groups.
Don't be crazy.
>> No. Groups like the Chinook and the
Schumash built permanent settlements not
because they were farmers, but because
they were able to find metric buttloads
of food in the ocean and the surrounding
environment that made sedentary
societies possible. So that's just a
sampling of what everything was like in
the Americas up to 1491. But hold on to
your butts because it's 1492 and here
come the Europeans. And they didn't just
show up for poops and giggles. No, there
were in fact many causes which I will
consolidate here under the headings of
gold, God, and glory. And let's look at
each in turn. So, the Europeans showed
up to the Americas for gold, which is to
say they had economic motives. A long
story short, prior to this period,
Europe was kind of like the hei of world
powers, just sort of along for the ride,
not really contributing anything
meaningful to the story and good for a
chuckle now and then. But then came the
Renaissance with all of its innovations
and cultural changes, and all of a
sudden, Europeans wanted to get fitted
for some power pants. Now, the first
problem they had was that in 1453, the
Ottoman Empire went ahead and gained
control over the land routes that
connected Europe to Asia for trade. And
that meant that Europeans couldn't get
the goods they wanted anymore on their
own terms without going through an
annoying middleman. So they got cranking
to figure out how to get to the Asian
and Southeast Asian markets via the sea
to cut out the aforementioned annoying
middleman. Now they were able to do this
because of two developments. First was
new techniques in ship building and the
adoption of maritime technology. The
Portuguese, for example, developed a new
kind of ship called the Caravl, which
was fast and highly navigable thanks to
its use of the Latin sail, which could
take wind from both directions. and
European navigators made use of older
Arab and Chinese technologies like the
magnetic compass which reckoned
direction and the astrolab which
reckoned latitude. All right. Now, the
second development was the rise of joint
stock companies to fund exploration
among several European powers.
Basically, a joint stock company was
funded by several investors as opposed
to a single source of funding like a
government. It turned out that when
these explorations went well, it was
fabulously profitable. But when they
failed, everything was lost. So, joint
stock companies made it so that many
investors could pull their wealth in
order to fund an expedition. And if it
failed, they would only lose their
portion. But if it succeeded, then huh,
we going to Disney World, y'all. Anyway,
it turned out that Portugal would be the
first to try out their sea legs. And
that ended up paying handsomely. Under
the leadership of Prince Henry the
Navigator, the Portuguese decided to try
sailing around Africa to access the
riches of the Indian Ocean trade. And as
they sailed around Africa, they
established permanent trading posts
along the coast where they would trade
goods with various African groups. In
doing so, they established what's known
as a trading post empire, which was
really about controlling these small
strategic posts as opposed to
establishing full-blown colonies. So,
this was going real good for Portugal,
and they were gaining embarrassing
amounts of wealth. So, Spain was like,
"Dang, we got to get us some of that."
But Spain had a problem. You see,
Portugal had already gotten control of
the strategic points around Africa and
into the Indian Ocean. So, the only
option was to sail west across the
Atlantic. But, they couldn't do it cuz
the Earth was all flat.
>> No, Derek. Everybody knew that the earth
was round during this period, mainly
because that problem had been solved by
the ancient stinking Greeks. Anyway,
that's when an Italian sailor named
Christopher Columbus showed up to the
Spanish corps looking for money to fund
an expedition westward to reach Asian
markets. And at that, the monarchs of
Spain, Ferdinand, and Isabella were
like, and so off Columbus went. And in
October of 1492, he reached an island in
the Caribbean. And thinking he had
reached the East Indies, he called the
indigenous people Indians. Now, even
after returning three more times, he
never stopped believing that he had
reached Asia. It fell to other Spanish
explorers like Amergo Vaspuchcci to
confirm that what Columbus had stumbled
upon was in fact a new world hitherto
unknown to Europeans. Anyway, Spain
started colonizing the Americas quick,
fast, and in a hurry. And since we're
still talking about economic motives for
exploration, let's focus on that. Spain
sent concistadors to the Americas to
subdue populations and find wealth. And
as it turns out, they very much did. For
example, Hernand Cortez toppled the
Aztec Empire with only a few hundred
men. And I'll get to the reasons for
that later. And then Francisco Pizaro
did the same thing down with the Inca
Empire. And both ventures resulted in
metric buttloads of gold and silver
being sent back to Spain which made them
wealthy beyond belief. But that wealth
also fundamentally transformed European
social and economic realities. The
biggest effect of this influx of wealth
was that it hastened the end of
feudalism and replaced it with
capitalism. And essentially the
difference between the two is this. In
feudalism, land equals wealth and
status. In capitalism, capital or owning
the means of production equals wealth.
So this was a pretty big change.
Although to be fair, feudalism was
already on the way out, but these
developments definitely helped it out
the door. Anyway, we need to spend a
little more time with Spain's economic
motives because they were very much
winning the imperialism game in the
Americas. It's pretty easy to argue that
Spain would not have continued to fund
voyages to the Americas if it were not
for the prodigious amounts of wealth
coming in as was reflected in a common
proverb from the time.
>> As long as y'all got the G's, we'll keep
sending the C. Sees are sure for
concisadors. I'm sure it's a lot more
elegant in the Spanish. Anyway, it's
true that initially Spain's wealth came
in the form of gold and silver. However,
they soon found that agriculture and the
export of cash crops would be a massive
money maker in addition to the export of
precious metal. And so, they imposed
various labor systems onto their
colonies, only one of which I'm going to
tell you about. It was called incomend,
and by definition, it was a system of
coerced labor in which the Spanish crown
granted tracks of land to Spanish
colonists known as incomanderos who
forced indigenous people within its
borders into plantation-based
agriculture and mining. More said in
simpler terms, the Spanish government
gave their colonizers a plot of land to
farm and whatever indigenous people
happened to live on that land became the
farmer's band of slave labor. But you
know, in return for that labor, the
incomanderos were supposed to provide
protection and Christian education to
the indigenous populations. But as these
things go, it really just became a form
of communal slavery. And on these
plantations, they grew highly profitable
crops like sugarcane and tobacco and
cotton, etc. And now that this colonial
machine was just printing cash for the
Spanish, it became a real problem when
indigenous laborers kept running away or
dying from disease. And I'll talk more
about that in a moment. Anyway, in order
to keep the wealth flowing, Spain
gradually replaced indigenous slaves
with enslaved African laborers. Spanish
merchants and other colonial powers as
well partnered with West African groups
in order to trade goods. Guns being the
most desirable good for enslaved
Africans from the interior of the
continent who were often captured in
wars or raids. Many of the African
groups involved in the trade of people
became wealthy and also powerful owing
to the superior weaponry they gained in
trading with the Europeans. And so
gradually enslaved Africans became the
dominant labor system in Spanish America
and Spanish wealth only continued to
increase. Okay. Now the last thing you
need to know under this heading in
reference to Spain is how they kept
control of their American colonies. And
one of the most significant means of
control was the Spanish cast system
which was a complete reorganization of
the social structure of societies in the
Americas according to a race-based
hierarchy. Now, to be clear, this kind
of structure was not in place among
indigenous peoples before the Spanish
came. It was wholesale slapped upon them
by the invading Spanish in an attempt to
maintain control of their wealth
producing opportunities. And I'll keep
it real simple. The folks on top of the
hierarchy were Spaniards, especially
those who were actually born in Spain.
At the bottom were indigenous and
African people. And then there were
various levels in the middle that
represented mixed race people who were
the result of European, you know,
contact. Basically, the more white blood
a person had, the purer they were
considered to be and therefore higher on
the hierarchy and vice versa. And that
brings us to the second cause of
European exploration, namely God, which
is to say there were also religious
motivations. Now, to really understand
this, you have to know that during this
time, much of Europe was in the middle
of a religious crisis and lots of
instability that came along with it. So,
the dominant belief system in Europe
since the dang Roman Empire was
Christianity, which was represented by
the Roman Catholic Church. And yes,
there was a major split in the church in
the 11th century, but we're going to
leave that to the side for our purposes.
All you really need to know is that
after that split, Western Europe became
the bastion of Roman Catholicism. But in
1517, a saucy Catholic monk by the name
of Martin Luther went ahead and started
the Protestant Reformation, which split
the Christian church in Europe. Once
again, the point is European states were
choosing sides as Catholic or
Protestant. The conflict was highly
charged as religious conflicts tend to
be. And during that time in Europe, the
church and state were about as close
together as a can of sardines in a
hydraulic press, which is to say, the
church and the state were not separate
entities at all. Therefore, since there
were now two belief systems fighting for
dominance, and since those belief
systems were tied very closely to the
state, European leaders were very
concerned to show that their particular
version of Christianity was better than
the other. And what better way to do
that than to gobble up a bunch of
colonies around the world and convert
folks to your particular flavor of
belief. Case in point, Spain. In 1469,
Christian Spain was unified when
Isabella of Castile and Ferdinand II of
Aragon got married. And then they got
busy leading the Reconista, which by
1492 had reconquered all areas formerly
under Muslim control, uniting Spain as a
Catholic state. Sacramento high fives
all around, y'all. And so the glory of
that victory got them real itchy to
spread Catholic Christianity as far as
they could. And I hope you're starting
to connect the dots by now because what
else happened in Spain in 1492?
Christopher Columbus showed up before
the Spanish court looking for money to
sail west. And so as the Spanish got
their American empire running, they sent
metric buttloads of Catholic
missionaries right along with the
concistadors in order to convert the
native populations to Christianity. Now
keep that in your back pocket because
we're going to come back to it in a
minute. But for now, let's consider the
final cause of European exploration,
which is, say it with me, glory. Or if
you're not that sassy, you could say
that these are the political motives. So
once contact was made between the old
and new worlds, it quickly became a
competition between European states to
acquire colonial possessions in order to
shift the balance of power in their
favor. Additionally, political change
was occurring in some European states in
which large multithnic empires were
breaking apart while some kingdoms were
becoming united and more powerful. And
that new political reality in which a
state ruled over a people with similar
language and culture and history was
known as the nation state. Anyway, these
political changes meant that European
powers were eager to be the greatest on
the world stage. And the way to become
great was to build maritime empires. And
as you might expect, that eventually
caused some tension. And a good example
here would be the spat between Portugal
and Spain over their respective New
World claims. Long story short, Portugal
was getting a little saucy over the fact
that Spain was gobbling up colonial
territory in the Americas that belonged
to Portugal. So, they did what any
Christian state would do and geared up a
fleet of ships to go blow Spain's crap
up. But since they were both Catholic
states, the Pope got involved and
settled their dispute by drawing a line
of demarcation, which settled the
question of which new world territories
belong to whom. In 1494, the line was
moved slightly and codified in the
Treaty of Tores, which established
Portugal's claim over a part of Brazil
and Spain's claim to dang near every
other part of the Americas, much of
which they didn't even know was there
yet. Now, conspicuously absent from
these negotiations were the indigenous
Americans themselves. And I think it's
safe to say that they were not nearly as
stoked about the treaty as were the
Spanish and the Portuguese. And I'll get
back to that, but for now, I need to
tell you about perhaps one of the most
significant effects of European
exploration during this period. That's
right, it's everybody's favorite inter
oceanic transfer, the Columbian
Exchange. And let's start with a
definition. The Columbian Exchange
refers to the transfer of plants,
animals, minerals, diseases, and people
between the old and new world. And in
case you don't know, the old world is
how Europeans refer to their world,
namely Afrourasia. New world is how
Europeans refer to the Americas, despite
the fact that the Americas were every
bit as old as the old world. But, you
know, whatever. Anyway, maybe the
transfer of stuff between old and new
worlds doesn't sound like much of a big
deal to you. Those guys got a potato.
Those guys got a turkey. Who cares?
Well, my dear pupil, allow me to explain
because the Columbian exchange was
arguably the most significant
demographic and environmental and
ecological change that you'll have the
pleasure of studying in all of world
history. So, let's start with a transfer
of disease. Now, because folks
throughout Afroureurasia, or if you're
sassy, the old world, because they had
been in contact for millennia, they had
developed immunities to each other's
nasty cooties. However, because of the
isolation of indigenous peoples of the
Americas, the diseases Europeans
introduced were devastating. Small pox
was the most devastating disease and it
was first introduced to the Caribbean by
Spanish explorers. Eventually, it spread
throughout Mexico and Central America
and killed around half the indigenous
population there and then spread into
South America with similar devastating
results. In fact, evidence suggests that
by 1600, some indigenous populations
were reduced by 90%. So now tying it all
together, you can see why Spanish
concistadors were able to conquer such
massive empires with relatively few men.
When they introduced smallox, it
weakened resistance significantly. And
also this is a big reason the encoma
system was replaced by African slavery
like many of the indigenous slaves were
dying of smallpox. Okay. The second
major transfer that occurred during the
colombian exchange included food and
plants and this transfer had major
effects on both old and new world. So
for example European settlers brought
wheat and olives and grapes which were
staple of European diets. Eventually
they also introduced African and Asian
foods like rice and bananas and sugar.
And then new world crops were also
transferred to Europe foods like maize
and potatoes and mania. And so the
introduction of these nutrient-rich
foods contributed to healthier
populations in Europe, which led to a
population explosion after 1700. Okay,
third on the transfer list was animals.
And by far the most significant were the
animals introduced by Europeans into the
Americas. Livestock like pigs and sheep
and cattle were introduced and because
they had no natural predators in the
Western Hemisphere, they multiplied
rapidly. As a result, indigenous farmers
were faced with the destruction of their
environment as freeranging animals
trampled and grazed on their crops. But
by far the most impactful animal to be
introduced to the Americas by the
Spanish was the horse. Indigenous groups
in the great plains like the Apaches and
the Comanches and the Kyas used the
horse to more effectively hunt large
herds of buffalo which was a staple food
item for them. Additionally, horses also
significantly changed warfare tactics
and bonus that change had the effect of
increasing violent conflict between
various tribes and between European and
indigenous groups. The introduction of
the horse was a change that
fundamentally altered their way of life.
And then the fourth item to know in the
Columbian exchange was minerals, mainly
gold and silver. Now, before the Spanish
discovered that cash cropping would earn
them a great deal of wealth in the
Americas, their main focus was on
extracting gold and silver from their
colonial holdings. And I already talked
about this when we talked about the gold
motivation for exploration. So, you
know, I'll just leave it at that. And
finally, the fifth major transfer was
people. Now, some indigenous Americans
were brought back to Europe. But by far
the bigger impact was the millions of
enslaved Africans transferred to
colonial America in order to work the
cash crop plantation. After having to
endure the brutality of the dreaded
middle passage across the Atlantic
Ocean, they were met with equally brutal
conditions as they were forced to work
the fields. Okay, here in the last
section, let's tie it all up by
considering a handful of effects that
occurred as a result of this interaction
between the old and new world. And right
out of the gate, you need to know that
as contact between Europeans and the
various indigenous peoples of the
Americas increased, it became clear that
their worldviews were very different. Or
to say it plainly, these two groups saw
the world completely different from each
other. And you're going to need to know
four examples. First, Europeans and
indigenous people held drastically
differing views on land use. Europeans
believed that land could be owned by
individuals, but the dominant indigenous
belief was that land was a resource
available to all and had a kind of
spiritual quality to it, like a source
of life, not a commodity available for
private ownership. Second, they held
different views on religion. As I
mentioned before, Europeans were on the
whole Christian and adhered to a complex
set of dogmas and doctrines, most
notably the doctrine of a single God.
And although indigenous belief systems
varied, many of them believed in
multiple gods and spirits that inhabited
and connected all living things. And
therefore, they did not separate the
spiritual and material realms as was
common in European Christianity. And
then third, we've got differing views on
gender roles. Europeans tended to be
patriarchal whereas indigenous people
tended to be more egalitarian even to
the extent that some family and power
structures were matrinal. And while
indigenous men and women often held
different roles in society, every
individual played a vital role. And
fourth, they held different views on
family. European's concept of family,
especially in Western Europe, emphasized
the nuclear family, whereas indigenous
peoples lived together in extended
families, which emphasized the
importance of shared responsibility in
child raising and respect for elders and
cultural transmission. And so, all that
to say, most of the early years of
contact between Europeans and indigenous
groups were full of misunderstandings as
they sought to make sense out of each
other. But eventually, in some cases,
Europeans and Native Americans adopted
some useful aspects of each other's
culture. For example, due to the Spanish
effort to establish Christian missions
in southwest North America, many
indigenous peoples converted to
Christianity. Now, it's certainly
arguable that these conversions occurred
due to the heavy-handed and sometimes
brutal tactics of the Spanish
missionaries. You better give your heart
to Jesus cuz your butt is mine. However,
being polytheists, the indigenous people
saw no conflict in adding the Christian
God to the worship of their other gods.
For example, the Virgin of Guadalupe
incorporates important aspects both of
Christian and Aztec religious
traditions. Or maybe it was enticing for
the indigenous people to convert to
Christianity when they observed that the
Spanish remained largely unaffected by
the epidemics killing large portions of
the indigenous population. So maybe they
were like, "What's the harm of adding
our boy Jesus to the mix of our other
gods?" Well, as it turned out, the
Spanish missionaries could not abide
Jesus being honored among other gods as
an equal. And so some of them resorted
to brutal tactics to bring indigenous
people into Christian orthodoxy. Okay.
Now, on the other side, European
settlers adopted useful aspects of
indigenous culture. For example, the
English settlers in North America just
about died before natives of the region
taught them local agricultural
techniques. And French settlers, mostly
interested in the robust American fur
trade, often intermarried with
indigenous women in order to firm up
trade relations, which I maintain is
about the most fairy tale reason to get
married that I've ever heard. But big
butt, massive butt, you have to know
that even though the invading Europeans
turned out to be a pretty powerful bunch
that got much of what they wanted in the
Americas, indigenous people did resist
their intrusion. And that basically
happened in two ways. First, some
indigenous groups engaged in diplomatic
negotiations by allying with certain
European groups in order to protect
themselves. This occurred when several
groups under Aztec power allied with the
Spanish in order to topple the Aztecs.
And second, there was military
resistance. Now, the Pueblo revolt won't
happen till the next period, but it is a
great example of indigenous people
getting fed up with Spanish efforts to
erase their culture and full-on
defeating them in battle. But in this
period, a good example is the Tino
Rebellion. So in 1511, the native people
of modern-day Puerto Rico rebelled
against the Spanish because they had
grown tired of the brutal conditions of
the Encomienda system and the threat to
their cultural traditions as the Spanish
attempted to convert them to
Christianity. Now the Tino were much
greater in number than the Spanish and
initially they had some success, but
ultimately the superior Spanish weaponry
won the day. And then the last effective
contact that I need to mention is this
debate over the status of Native
Americans and Africans. So after this
prolonged contact between Europeans and
Native Americans and Africans, a debate
rose among Europeans about whether the
brutal conditions of slavery either
through the incoming system or African
slavery was justified. And in Spain, the
status of indigenous people was argued
in the viadelid debates. On one side was
Barthole de lasas. Upon his arrival to
the Americas, he actually owned
indigenous slaves and even fought a war
against them. However, over time, he
became one of their chief advocates in
Spain. He argued that indigenous people
were fully human and thus ought not to
be subject to the inhumane ravages of
systems like incomienda. On the other
side was Juan Guin de Seepovveda who
argued that indigenous people were in
fact less than human and as such
benefited from service to Europeans. And
so it's important to realize that this
debate among the religious folk revealed
that there was no singular agreement on
exactly who these indigenous people were
since they were not mentioned in the
Bible and therefore there's no clear
instruction on how they ought to be
treated. And ultimately that question
remained. But Europeans were able to
develop novel justifications for their
harsh treatment of Africans and
indigenous people. For example, in order
to justify the brutality of African
slavery, Christians turned to the Bible,
specifically an event known as the curse
of Ham. In the story, God curses Noah's
son Ham to be a servant of his brothers.
And it was said that God put a mark on
him to signify his servitude. Now, the
story doesn't say what the mark was, but
Christians seeking to justify slavery
decided that the mark must be dark skin,
and that was enough for them to continue
their brutal policies toward African and
indigenous people. All right, click here
to watch my other unit one videos and
click here to get your hands on my A
push Himler review guide, which is the
fastest way to study. And hey, I'll
catch you on the flip-flop.